<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Mahout | SequenceIQ Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.sequenceiq.com/blog/categories/mahout/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.sequenceiq.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-13T12:27:55+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.sequenceiq.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SequenceIQ]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Mahout with Tez]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.sequenceiq.com/blog/2014/03/31/mahout-on-tez/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-31T10:22:09+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.sequenceiq.com/blog/2014/03/31/mahout-on-tez</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At SequenceIQ we are always open to the latest innovations in Hadoop, and trying to find a way to offer a better performance and cluster utilization to our customers. We came in close touch with the <a href="http://hortonworks.com/labs/stinger/">Stinger initiative</a> last year at the Hadoop Summit in Amsterdam &ndash; and ever since we have followed up with the project progress (latest <a href="http://hortonworks.com/blog/apache-tez-0-3-released/">release</a> is 0.3). The project was initiated by Hortonworks with the goal of a 100x performance improvement of Hive.
Although Hive is not part of our product stack (we use other ways for SQL on Hadoop), there is one particular key component of the Stinger initiative which was very interesting to us: <a href="https://github.com/apache/incubator-tez">Apache Tez</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://incubator.apache.org/projects/tez.html">Apache Tez</a> is a new application framework built on top of Hadoop Yarn that can execute complex directed acyclic graphs (DAGs) of general data processing tasks. In many ways it can be thought of as a more flexible and powerful successor of the map-reduce framework. This was exactly what draw our attention and made us start thinking about using Tez as our runtime for map-reduce jobs.</p>

<h2>Tez and MapReduce</h2>

<p>At SequenceIQ we have chains of map-reduce jobs which are scheduled individually and read the output of previous jobs from HBase or HDFS. Many times our map-reduce job flow can be represented as a map-reduce-reduce pattern, however building complex job chains with the current map-reduce framework is not that easy (nor saves on performance) &ndash; we combined the ChainMapper/ChainReducer and IdentityMapper trying to build MRR like DAG job flows.</p>

<p>In Tez data coming from reducers' output can be pipelined together and eliminates IO/sync barriers, as no temporary HDFS write is required. Jobs can also be chained and represented as MRR steps with no restriction.
In MapReduce disregarding the data size, the shuffle (internal step between the map and reducer) phase writes the sorted partitions to disk, merge-sorts them and feed into the reducers. All these steps are done <em>in memory</em> with Tez and saves on this I/O heavy step, avoiding unnecessary temporary writes and reads.</p>

<h2>Tez and Mahout</h2>

<p>Part of our system is running machine learning algorithms in batch, using Mahout (we do ML on streaming data using Scala, MLlib and Apache Spark as well). To improve the runtime performance of these Mahout algorithms, and decrease the cluster execution time we started to experiment with combining Tez and Mahout, and rewrite a few Mahout drivers in order to build DAGs of MR jobs (MRR in particular where applicable) and submit the jobs in a Tez runtime on a YARN cluster.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>In this blog post we would like to introduce you to Tez &ndash; for your convenience we have put together a Hadoop 2.3/YARN/Tez  <a href="https://github.com/sequenceiq/tez-docker">Tez-Docker</a> image &ndash; where the Tez runtime is already pre-configured. We have submitted a Mahout classification job into a YARN cluster as a regular MR job and then resubmitted the same job into Tez on a YARN cluster. Finally we made some metrics to highlight the differences: both in elapsed time and resource utilization.</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t want to use this docker image, you should configure Tez on your Hadoop cluster first.</p>

<h3>Building Tez</h3>

<p>Get the Tez code from <a href="https://github.com/apache/incubator-tez">GitHub</a>, and run <code>mvn clean install -DskipTests=true -Dmaven.javadoc.skip=true</code>. Alternatively you can get the jars from <a href="https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/seq-tez/tez-0.3.0-incubating.tar.gz">SequenceIQ S3</a> and copy into HDFS under the &lsquo;/usr/lib/tez&rsquo; folder.</p>

<h3>Add *-site.xml</h3>

<p>Add <a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/sequenceiq/tez-docker/master/tez-site.xml">tez-site.xml</a> and <a href="https://github.com/sequenceiq/tez-docker/blob/master/mapred-site.xml">mapred-site.xml</a> to Hadoop (in case of the docker image it&rsquo;s $HADOOP_PREFIX/etc/hadoop/).</p>

<h3>Add Tez jars and config to HADOOP_CLASSPATH</h3>

<p>Edit your hadoop-env.sh file by executing this script:</p>

<p><code>bash
echo 'TEZ_JARS=/usr/local/tez/*' &gt;&gt; $HADOOP_PREFIX/etc/hadoop/hadoop-env.sh
echo 'TEZ_LIB=/usr/local/tez/lib/*' &gt;&gt; $HADOOP_PREFIX/etc/hadoop/hadoop-env.sh
echo 'TEZ_CONF=/usr/local/hadoop/etc/hadoop' &gt;&gt; $HADOOP_PREFIX/etc/hadoop/hadoop-env.sh
echo 'export HADOOP_CLASSPATH=$HADOOP_CLASSPATH:$TEZ_CONF:$TEZ_JARS:$TEZ_LIB' &gt;&gt; $HADOOP_PREFIX/etc/hadoop/hadoop-env.sh
</code></p>

<p>Make sure you set your HADOOP_PREFIX env variable, or use <a href="http://ambari.apache.org/">Apache Ambari</a> to configure Tez (change the mapreduce.framework.name property to yarn-tez).</p>

<h3>Submit a classification job &ndash; get the code and instructions from the SequenceIQ samples <em><a href="https://github.com/sequenceiq/sequenceiq-samples/tree/master/tez-dag-jobs">GitHub</a></em> page.</h3>

<p>After running the job and collecting the metrics we will see that the differences between using MapReduce and Tez are quite significant (~10x faster with Tez).</p>

<p>Below you can see the sample Mahout classification job submitted in YARN using MapReduce.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/sequenceiq/sequenceiq-samples/master/tez-dag-jobs/resources/Classification_Mahout_MR.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Below you can see the sample Mahout classification job submitted in YARN using Tez.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/sequenceiq/sequenceiq-samples/master/tez-dag-jobs/resources/Classification_Mahout_TEZ.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>If we dig into deeper metrics we can see the huge differences between the file operations and HDFS I/O. The Tez framework does way less file operations as the MapReduce one.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/sequenceiq/sequenceiq-samples/master/tez-dag-jobs/resources/fileops_tez_vs_mr.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Also if we check the HDFS I/O operations we see the same results &ndash; less and more efficient HDFS operations in case of Tez.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/sequenceiq/sequenceiq-samples/master/tez-dag-jobs/resources/hdfsio_tez_vs_mr.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>All these are because the Tez runtime is using in-memory operations whenever is possible instead of temporarily persisting the sorted partitions to HDFS.
Tez and <a href="http://hortonworks.com/labs/stinger/">Hortonworks' Stinger initiative</a> is opening up new possibilities to write faster and more performant Hadoop jobs, and closes the gap between stream and batch processing.</p>

<p>We are in the middle of rewriting &ndash; and sharing with the Hadoop community all the Mahout drivers we use &ndash; to Apache Tez. Also we are in the middle of proof-of-concepting our Scala/Scalding based map-reduce jobs to use Tez as a runtime.</p>

<p>Follow up with this <a href="http://blog.sequenceiq.com/">blog</a> and visit our <a href="https://github.com/sequenceiq/sequenceiq-samples/tree/master/tez-dag-jobs">GitHub</a> page for further details.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
