<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: SOCKS proxy | SequenceIQ Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.sequenceiq.com/blog/categories/socks-proxy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.sequenceiq.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-02T18:57:21+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.sequenceiq.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SequenceIQ]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Accessing HDP2 sandbox from the host]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.sequenceiq.com/blog/2014/03/05/access-hdp2-sandbox/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-05T08:12:44+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.sequenceiq.com/blog/2014/03/05/access-hdp2-sandbox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During development of a Hadoop project people have many options of where and how to run Hadoop. We at SequenceIQ use different environments as well (cloud based, VM or host) &ndash; and different versions/vendor distributions. A very popular distribution among developers is the Hortonworks Sandbox &ndash; which contains the latest releases across Hadoop (2.2.0) and the key related projects into a single integrated and tested platform.
While using the sandbox gets you going running a single node Hadoop (pseudo distributed) in less than 5 minutes, many developers find inconvenient to &lsquo;live&rsquo; and work inside the VM when deploying, debugging or submitting jobs into a Hadoop cluster.</p>

<p>There is a well documented VM host file configuration on the <a href="http://docs.hortonworks.com/">Hortonworks site</a> describing how to start interacting with the VM sandbox from outside (e.g host machine), but quite soon this will turn into a port-forwarding saga (those who know how many ports does Hadoop and the ecosystem use will know what we mean). An easier and more elegant way is to use a SOCKS5 proxy (which comes with SSL by default).
Check this short goal/problem/resolution and code example snippet if you&rsquo;d like to interact with the Hortonworks Sandbox from your host (outside the VM).</p>

<h2>Goal</h2>

<ul>
<li>accessing the pseudo distributed hadoop cluster from the  host</li>
<li>reading / writing to the  HDFS</li>
<li>submitting  M/R jobs to the RM</li>
</ul>


<h2>Problem(s)</h2>

<ul>
<li>it&rsquo;s hard to reach resources inside the sandbox (e.g. interact with HDFS, or the DataNode)</li>
<li>lots of ports need to be portforwarded</li>
<li>entries to be added to the hosts file of the  host machine</li>
<li>circumstantial configuration of clients  accessing the sandbox</li>
</ul>


<h2>Resolution</h2>

<ul>
<li>use an SSL socks proxy</li>
</ul>


<h2>Example</h2>

<ul>
<li>check the following sample from our <em><a href="https://github.com/sequenceiq/sequenceiq-samples/tree/master/hdp-sandbox-access">GitHub page</a></em></li>
</ul>


<p>Start the SOCKS proxy</p>

<p><code>bash
ssh root@127.0.0.1 -p 2222 -D 1099
</code></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Once the proxy is up and running, edit the core-site.xml</p>

<p>``` xml</p>

<pre><code>    &lt;property&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;hadoop.socks.server&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;value&gt;localhost:1099&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;hadoop.rpc.socket.factory.class.default&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;value&gt;org.apache.hadoop.net.SocksSocketFactory&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Now you can run the test client</p>

<p>``` bash</p>

<h1>You can use Maven</h1>

<p>mvn exec:java -Dexec.mainClass=&ldquo;com.sequenceiq.samples.SandboxTester&rdquo; -Dexec.args=&ldquo;hdfs sandbox 8020&rdquo; -Dhadoop.home.dir=/tmp</p>

<h1>or run from the JAR file</h1>

<p>java -jar sandbox-playground-1.0.jar hdfs sandbox 8020
```</p>

<p>As you see it&rsquo;s pretty easy and convenient to use the Hortonworks sandbox as a pre-configured development environment.</p>

<p>In case you&rsquo;d like to use (as we do most of the time) a Hadoop cluster in the cloud (Amazon EC2), check our previous blog post <a href="http://blog.sequenceiq.com/blog/2014/02/07/hdp2-on-amazon/">HDP2 on Amazon</a>.
In case you ever wondered whether it&rsquo;s possible to use Hadoop with Docker please follow this blog.</p>

<p>Hope this helps,
SequenceIQ</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
