<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Early access | SequenceIQ Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.sequenceiq.com/blog/categories/early-access/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.sequenceiq.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-20T13:58:32+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.sequenceiq.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SequenceIQ]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Apache Ambari 1.7.0 early access]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.sequenceiq.com/blog/2014/09/05/apache-ambari-1-7-0-ea/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-05T16:37:37+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.sequenceiq.com/blog/2014/09/05/apache-ambari-1-7-0-ea</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At <a href="http://sequenceiq.com/">SequenceIQ</a> we use <a href="http://ambari.apache.org/">Apache Ambari</a> every day &ndash; it’s our tool to provision Hadoop clusters.</p>

<p>Beside that we are contributors to Ambari, we are so excited about the coming Apache Ambari 1.7.0 new <a href="https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=30755705">features</a> that we could not help and put together an <strong>early access</strong> <a href="https://github.com/sequenceiq/docker-ambari/tree/1.7.0-ea">Ambari 1.7.0 Docker container</a>.</p>

<p>Give it a try, and provision an arbitrary number of Hadoop cluster on your laptop (or production environment), using our container and Ambari shell. Let us know how it works for you. Enjoy.</p>

<h3>Get the Docker container</h3>

<p>In case you don’t have Docker browse among our previous posts &ndash; we have a few posts about howto’s, examples and best practices in general for Docker and in particular about how to run the full Hadoop stack on Docker.</p>

<p><code>
docker pull sequenceiq/ambari:1.7.0-ea
</code></p>

<!--more-->


<p>Once you have the container you are almost ready to go &ndash; we always automate everything and <strong>over simplify</strong> Hadoop provisioning.</p>

<h3>Get ambari-functions</h3>

<p>Get the following <code>ambari-functions</code> <a href="https://github.com/sequenceiq/docker-ambari/blob/1.7.0-ea/ambari-functions">file</a> from our GitHub.</p>

<p><code>
curl -Lo .amb j.mp/docker-ambari-170ea &amp;&amp; . .amb
</code></p>

<h3>Create your cluster</h3>

<p><code>
amb-deploy-cluster 4
</code></p>

<p><strong>Whaaat?</strong> No really, that’s it &ndash; we have just provisioned you a 4 node Hadoop cluster in less than 2 minutes. Docker, Apache Ambari and Ambari Shell combined is quite powerful, isn&rsquo;t it? You can always start playing with your desired services by changing the <a href="https://github.com/sequenceiq/ambari-rest-client/tree/master/src/main/resources/blueprints">blueprints</a> &ndash; the full Hadoop stack is supported.</p>

<p>If you’d like to play around and understand how this works check our previous blog posts &ndash; a good start is this first post about one of our contribution, the <a href="http://blog.sequenceiq.com/blog/2014/05/26/ambari-shell/">Ambari Shell</a>.</p>

<p>You have just seen how easy is to provision a Hadoop cluster on your laptop, if you’d like to see how we provision a Hadoop cluster in the cloud using the very same Docker image you can check our open source, cloud agnostic Hadoop as a Service API &ndash; <a href="http://blog.sequenceiq.com/blog/2014/07/18/announcing-cloudbreak/">Cloudbreak</a>. Last week we have released a project called <a href="http://blog.sequenceiq.com/blog/2014/08/27/announcing-periscope/">Periscope</a> &ndash; the industry&rsquo;s first open source autoscaling API for Hadoop.</p>

<p>For updates follow us on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/sequenceiq/">LinkedIn</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/sequenceiq">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://www.facebook.com/sequenceiq">Facebook</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
